<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<index>
  <info>
    <name>Way of Bird of Hermes</name>
    <description>Monastic Tradition Subvariant - Bird of Hermes (Homebrew)</description>
    <author>Batuhan Takır</author>
    <update version="1.0" />
  </info>

  <elements>
    <info>
      <name>Way of Bird of Hermes</name>
      <description>Monastic Tradition Subvariant for Monk - Bird of Hermes</description>
      <author>Batuhan Takır</author>
      <version>1.0</version>
    </info>

    <element name="Way of Bird of Hermes" type="Archetype" source="Homebrew" id="ID_HOMEBREW_MONK_TRADITION_BIRD_OF_HERMES">
      <supports>Monastic Tradition</supports>
      <prerequisite>Monk</prerequisite>
      <description>The Bird of Hermes Monks follow the path of the Astral Self, embracing their inner will and sacrificing their wings to gain true freedom.
They are philosophers of volition and pain — to master oneself is to conquer restraint.

"Bird of Hermes is my name, eating my wings to make me tame."</description>
      <sheet display="false" />
    </element>

    <element name="Wings of Untamed Wind" type="Archetype Feature" source="Homebrew" id="ID_HOMEBREW_MONK_BIRD_OF_HERMES_WINGS_OF_UNTAMED_WIND">
      <supports>Monastic Tradition, Way of Bird of Hermes</supports>
      <prerequisite>Monk 3</prerequisite>
      <description>At 3rd level, you can spend 1 ki point as a bonus action to manifest spectral wings of wind and will for 10 minutes.
While active:
• You gain +10 ft flying speed (hover) and use Wisdom instead of Strength for Strength checks and saves.
• You can make unarmed strikes with the spectral wings; reach increases by 5 ft, and they deal force damage.
• Once per turn when you hit with the wings, you can make an additional unarmed strike as a bonus action without spending ki.
• You sense creatures within 15 ft through obstacles or darkness (as if using blindsense).</description>
    </element>

    <element name="Soul Dive" type="Archetype Feature" source="Homebrew" id="ID_HOMEBREW_MONK_BIRD_OF_HERMES_SOUL_DIVE">
      <supports>Monastic Tradition, Way of Bird of Hermes</supports>
      <prerequisite>Monk 5</prerequisite>
      <description>As a bonus action, spend 1 ki to teleport up to 15 feet to an unoccupied space you can see. This movement does not provoke opportunity attacks.</description>
    </element>

    <element name="Sword of the Messenger" type="Archetype Feature" source="Homebrew" id="ID_HOMEBREW_MONK_BIRD_OF_HERMES_SWORD_OF_THE_MESSENGER">
      <supports>Monastic Tradition, Way of Bird of Hermes</supports>
      <prerequisite>Monk 6</prerequisite>
      <description>You can summon a spectral blade of pure intent. As a bonus action, spend 1 ki to summon the Astral Blade for 10 minutes.
• Choose Force, Radiant, or Necrotic damage.
• Use Wisdom for attack and damage rolls (1d8 + Wis).
• On a hit, the target must make a Con save (DC 8 + Prof + Wis) or take +1d6 damage and lose resistances until your next turn.
• While the blade is active, you can see invisible creatures and have advantage on Insight and Intimidation checks.</description>
    </element>

    <element name="Iron Will" type="Archetype Feature" source="Homebrew" id="ID_HOMEBREW_MONK_BIRD_OF_HERMES_IRON_WILL">
      <supports>Monastic Tradition, Way of Bird of Hermes</supports>
      <prerequisite>Monk 9</prerequisite>
      <description>When a creature hits you with an attack, you can use your reaction and spend 1 ki to force the attacker to reroll, taking the lower result.
Reduce the damage you take by 1d10 + Wisdom modifier. If it still hits, half the remaining damage transfers to your spirit. Once per short rest (twice at 14th level).</description>
    </element>

    <element name="Will and the Blade" type="Archetype Feature" source="Homebrew" id="ID_HOMEBREW_MONK_BIRD_OF_HERMES_WILL_AND_BLADE">
      <supports>Monastic Tradition, Way of Bird of Hermes</supports>
      <prerequisite>Monk 11</prerequisite>
      <description>When both your spectral wings and blade are summoned, your astral body manifests. While active:
• You and your spirit can each attack once per turn.
• When you hit with the wings, deal extra damage equal to your Martial Arts die.
• Allies within 10 ft of your spirit gain temporary HP equal to your Wisdom modifier at the start of their turn.</description>
    </element>

    <element name="Soul Rend" type="Archetype Feature" source="Homebrew" id="ID_HOMEBREW_MONK_BIRD_OF_HERMES_SOUL_REND">
      <supports>Monastic Tradition, Way of Bird of Hermes</supports>
      <prerequisite>Monk 14</prerequisite>
      <description>When you slay a creature, you capture a fragment of its essence as a Soul Echo (max 3).
You can expend one echo to deal +1d8 force damage on a hit. All echoes fade after a long rest.</description>
    </element>

    <element name="Phoenix" type="Archetype Feature" source="Homebrew" id="ID_HOMEBREW_MONK_BIRD_OF_HERMES_PHOENIX">
      <supports>Monastic Tradition, Way of Bird of Hermes</supports>
      <prerequisite>Monk 17</prerequisite>
      <description>As a bonus action, spend 5 ki to awaken your full astral form for 10 minutes. While awakened:
• +2 AC.
• You can make 3 attacks with Extra Attack if all are with astral wings.
• All your attacks deal soul damage (ignoring resistances and immunities).
• On a critical hit, the target must make a Wisdom save (DC 8 + Prof + Wis) or be stunned until your next turn.
• If you would drop to 0 HP while awakened, you remain at 1 HP once per long rest.
• Each kill during this state heals allies within 10 ft equal to your Wisdom modifier.</description>
    </element>

    <element name="Messenger Thyself" type="Archetype Feature" source="Homebrew" id="ID_HOMEBREW_MONK_BIRD_OF_HERMES_MESSENGER_THYSELF">
      <supports>Monastic Tradition, Way of Bird of Hermes</supports>
      <prerequisite>Monk 20</prerequisite>
      <description>Upon death, your spirit continues to fight for 1 minute in awakened form. It regains HP each turn equal to your Wisdom modifier + half your Monk level.
If your spirit slays a creature during that time, your body revives with 1 HP. Once per long rest.</description>
    </element>

  </elements>
</index>
