<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<elements>
  <info>
    <name>Way of Bird of Hermes</name>
    <description>Monastic Tradition Subvariant for Monk - Bird of Hermes</description>
    <author>Uploaded by user; XML structured by ChatGPT</author>
    <version>1.0</version>
  </info>
  <element name="Way of Bird of Hermes" type="Archetype" source="Homebrew" id="ID_HOMEBREW_MONK_TRADITION_BIRD_OF_HERMES">
    <supports>Monastic Tradition</supports>
    <prerequisite>Monk</prerequisite>
    <description>The Disciple Bird of Hermes comes from the tradition: Way of the Astral Self and infuses it with the Soul Bird. Monks of this path relinquish their wings and reveal their astral form, a representation of their will. They are philosophers of volition and pain — to understand freedom, one must first touch pain.

&quot;Bird of Hermes is my name, cut thy wings to make me tame.&quot;</description>
    <sheet display="false"/>
  </element>
  <element name="Wings of Untamed Wind" type="Archetype Feature" source="Homebrew" id="ID_HOMEBREW_MONK_BIRD_OF_HERMES_WINGS_OF_UNTAMED_WIND">
    <supports>Monastic Tradition, Way of Bird of Hermes</supports>
    <prerequisite>Monk 3</prerequisite>
    <description>As a bonus action, spend 1 ki to summon spectral wings of untamed wind for 10 minutes (end early if you are incapacitated or die). Each creature of your choice within 10 feet makes a Dexterity save or takes force damage equal to two rolls of your Martial Arts die. The wings hover near your scaphoids. While active:
• You may use Wisdom instead of Strength for Strength checks and saving throws.
• You can make unarmed strikes with the spectral wings; reach with these attacks is increased by 5 feet.
• Attacks with the wings use Wisdom for attack and damage and deal force damage.
• Soul Sense: Sense living creatures within 15 feet (30 feet at 6th level) through walls/darkness (you feel presence, you do not see).
• Spirit Combo: When you hit with Untamed Wings, you can make one Unarmed Strike as a bonus action without spending ki (stacks with Martial Arts).
• Whispering Soul: Once per long rest, telepathically speak a short phrase to a creature within 30 feet.
• Spirit Infusion (from 4th level): Your Unarmed Strikes and Astral attacks count as magical for overcoming resistance and immunity.</description>
    <sheet>
      <description text="Wings of Untamed Wind"/>
    </sheet>
  </element>
  <element name="Soul Dive" type="Archetype Feature" source="Homebrew" id="ID_HOMEBREW_MONK_BIRD_OF_HERMES_SOUL_DIVE">
    <supports>Monastic Tradition, Way of Bird of Hermes</supports>
    <prerequisite>Monk 5</prerequisite>
    <description>As a bonus action, spend 1 ki to teleport up to 15 feet to an unoccupied space you can see. This movement does not provoke opportunity attacks.</description>
    <sheet>
      <description text="Soul Dive"/>
    </sheet>
  </element>
  <element name="Sword of the Messenger" type="Archetype Feature" source="Homebrew" id="ID_HOMEBREW_MONK_BIRD_OF_HERMES_SWORD_OF_THE_MESSENGER">
    <supports>Monastic Tradition, Way of Bird of Hermes</supports>
    <prerequisite>Monk 6</prerequisite>
    <description>You can summon the visage of your astral self (as per Arms/Visage of the Astral Self thematics). While the spectral visage is present:
• Astral Sight: See normally in magical and nonmagical darkness to 120 ft.
• Wisdom of the Spirit: Advantage on Wisdom (Insight) and Charisma (Intimidation) checks.
• Word of the Spirit: Direct your voice to one creature within 60 ft (only it hears) or amplify so all within 600 ft hear.

Astral Blade (Soul Reaver’s Edge): As a bonus action, spend 1 ki to summon a spectral blade for 10 minutes. Choose Force, Radiant, or Necrotic damage on summon. Use Wisdom for attack and damage; damage is 1d8 + Wisdom.
• Soul Wound: On a hit, target makes a Con save (DC 8 + Prof + Wis). On failure, it takes +1d6 damage and loses any resistances until the end of your next turn.
• Soul Edge: First successful hit each time you summon the blade deals an extra 1d4 + Wisdom (improves to 1d6 at 11th level, 1d8 at 17th).
• Soul Sever Utility: While the blade is active, you can see invisible creatures and sense living ones within 30 ft; the first attack against you each round has disadvantage as your spirit shields you.</description>
    <sheet>
      <description text="Sword of the Messenger"/>
    </sheet>
  </element>
  <element name="Iron Will" type="Archetype Feature" source="Homebrew" id="ID_HOMEBREW_MONK_BIRD_OF_HERMES_IRON_WILL">
    <supports>Monastic Tradition, Way of Bird of Hermes</supports>
    <prerequisite>Monk 9</prerequisite>
    <description>When a creature hits you with an attack, you can use your reaction and spend 1 ki to force the attacker to reroll the attack, taking the lower result. When you do so, reduce the damage you take by 1d10 + Wisdom modifier (minimum 1). If it still hits, half the damage is transferred to your spirit. Use once per short rest (twice at 14th level).</description>
    <sheet>
      <description text="Iron Will"/>
    </sheet>
  </element>
  <element name="Will and the Blade" type="Archetype Feature" source="Homebrew" id="ID_HOMEBREW_MONK_BIRD_OF_HERMES_WILL_AND_THE_BLADE">
    <supports>Monastic Tradition, Way of Bird of Hermes</supports>
    <prerequisite>Monk 11</prerequisite>
    <description>When you have both astral wings and blade summoned, the astral body manifests (no action). While present:
• Empowered Wings: Once per turn when you hit with Wings of Untamed Wind, deal extra damage equal to your Martial Arts die.
• Your spirit can move up to 50 ft away from you; both your body and spirit may each attack once per turn.
• Creatures within 10 ft of your spirit gain temp HP equal to your Wisdom modifier at the start of their turn.
• When your spirit scores a critical hit, your body gains advantage on its next attack.</description>
    <sheet>
      <description text="Will and the Blade"/>
    </sheet>
  </element>
  <element name="Soul Rend" type="Archetype Feature" source="Homebrew" id="ID_HOMEBREW_MONK_BIRD_OF_HERMES_SOUL_REND">
    <supports>Monastic Tradition, Way of Bird of Hermes</supports>
    <prerequisite>Monk 14</prerequisite>
    <description>When you slay a creature, capture a fragment of its essence as a Soul Echo (max 3). Expend a Soul Echo to deal +1d8 force damage on an attack (you may expend multiple). All echoes fade after a long rest.</description>
    <sheet>
      <description text="Soul Rend"/>
    </sheet>
  </element>
  <element name="Phoenix" type="Archetype Feature" source="Homebrew" id="ID_HOMEBREW_MONK_BIRD_OF_HERMES_PHOENIX">
    <supports>Monastic Tradition, Way of Bird of Hermes</supports>
    <prerequisite>Monk 17</prerequisite>
    <description>As a bonus action, spend 5 ki to fully awaken your astral self for 10 minutes (ends early if incapacitated or you die). While awakened:
• Armor of the Spirit: +2 bonus to AC.
• Astral Barrage: When you would make two attacks with Extra Attack, you can instead make three attacks if all are with your astral wings.
• All your attacks deal Soul Damage, ignoring resistance and immunity.
• On a critical hit, the target must make a Wisdom save (DC 8 + Prof + Wis) or be Stunned until the end of your next turn.
• The effect lasts for 1 minute.
• When the awakening ends, if you would drop to 0 HP, you instead remain at 1 HP (once per long rest).
• Each time you kill a creature during the awakening, allies within 10 ft regain HP equal to your Wisdom modifier.</description>
    <sheet>
      <description text="Phoenix"/>
    </sheet>
  </element>
  <element name="Messenger Thyself" type="Archetype Feature" source="Homebrew" id="ID_HOMEBREW_MONK_BIRD_OF_HERMES_MESSENGER_THYSELF">
    <supports>Monastic Tradition, Way of Bird of Hermes</supports>
    <prerequisite>Monk 20</prerequisite>
    <description>If you die, your spirit continues to fight for 1 minute in its awakened form. Your spirit regains HP each turn equal to your Wisdom modifier + half your Monk level. If your spirit slays a creature during this time, your body immediately revives with 1 HP. Once per long rest.</description>
    <sheet>
      <description text="Messenger Thyself"/>
    </sheet>
  </element>
  <element name="Optional Soul Techniques (Additions)" type="Archetype Feature" source="Homebrew" id="ID_HOMEBREW_MONK_BIRD_OF_HERMES_OPTIONAL_TECHNIQUES">
    <supports>Monastic Tradition, Way of Bird of Hermes</supports>
    <prerequisite>Monk 4+</prerequisite>
    <description>Optional Additions:
• Level 4: Spirit Infusion — Unarmed Strikes and Astral attacks count as magical.
• Level 5: Soul Step — Spend 1 Ki (Bonus Action) to teleport 15 ft without provoking opportunity attacks.
• Level 7+: Soul Tether — Bind a creature’s soul for 1 round; it can’t teleport or shift planes.
• Level 10+: Soul Pulse — Once per short rest, unleash a 10‑ft wave of spiritual energy for 2d8 + Wis force damage.
• Level 15+: Ki Devour — If a Soul‑Wounded target dies within 10 ft, regain 1 Ki point.</description>
    <sheet>
      <description text="Optional Soul Techniques (see description)"/>
    </sheet>
  </element>
</elements>
